<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Low Code &amp; Fusion Dev Blog</title>
        <link>https://microsoft.github.io/Low-Code/blog</link>
        <description>Low Code &amp; Fusion Dev Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <language>en</language>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[You say Low, I say Code!]]></title>
            <link>https://microsoft.github.io/Low-Code/blog/2023-day2</link>
            <guid>2023-day2</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[You say Low, I say Code!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="you-say-low-i-say-code">You say Low, I say Code!<a class="hash-link" href="#you-say-low-i-say-code" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>There is a low code revolution underway. We have a surging digital demand with an estimated 500 million more apps that will need to be created in the next 5 years. More and more companies are leveraging low code and no code platforms to bridge this app gap and address workflow and automation needs. In fact, Gartner estimates that 65% of application development will be low code by 2024.</p><p>With low code tools like the Power Platform making it easier for business technologists to develop solutions, you might wonder if there's any room for a code first developer in this low code revolution. Well, the answer is, absolutely there is! In fact, code first developers are a critical piece to the puzzle.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-is-low-code">What is "low code"?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-is-low-code" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The term "low code" can mean different things to different people when they first hear it. What we mean when we talk about low code is that with tools like Power Apps, you only need to write a small amount of code to get results that would normally take several more lines of code in a traditional programming language.</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="What is Low Code" src="/Low-Code/assets/images/02_WhatIsLowCode-4f9966b58f106fe0bb5d6d4da968dd5a.png" width="1937" height="1070" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>In canvas-based Power Apps, the low code scripting language used is called <a href="https://aka.ms/LearnPowerFx" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Power Fx</a>. This language is based on the Microsoft Excel formula language which meets many business technologists where they are by leveraging the knowledge they already have.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="low-code--full-code--no-cliffs">Low Code + Full Code = No Cliffs<a class="hash-link" href="#low-code--full-code--no-cliffs" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Using low-code tools is key to helping to resolve the existing and impending app gap challenge but that doesn't mean that low code alone can solve every business problem. Low code tools like the Power Platform's full potential is unlocked when you combine the low code capabilities with code first development.</p><p>The combination of low code + full code creates what we call a "no cliffs" experience that allows business technologists to easily build solutions with low code while professional developers can leverage full code to augment and extend the platform capabilities. The process of low code developers, IT pros and full code developers working together like this is often referred to as "fusion development".</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Fusion Development Process" src="/Low-Code/assets/images/02_FusionDevProcess-1d75a4cfd7019909a56ca5ca3499316d.png" width="1937" height="1070" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-does-the-power-platform-provide">What does the Power Platform Provide?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-does-the-power-platform-provide" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>The Power Platform gives us a holistic suite of low code tools that work together to help us solve business problems. The key products and components of the Power Platform include:</p><ul><li><strong>Power Apps</strong> for creating custom applications for web and mobile that can be integrated with a variety of systems and services.</li><li><strong>Power Automate</strong> for automation tasks and orchestrating activities across various services</li><li><strong>Power BI</strong> for business analytics and interactive data visualization</li><li><strong>Power Virtual Agents</strong> for creating AI-powered chatbots that can answer questions from your customers and employees</li><li><strong>Power Pages</strong> for secure, enterprise-grade external-facing business websites</li><li><strong>Dataverse</strong> which provides a cloud scale data store with robust security that abstracts away data management complexity from the app maker</li></ul><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Power Platform Overview" src="/Low-Code/assets/images/02_PowerPlatformOverview-78e3e950cd1ecb102d264eca0db14efa.png" width="1254" height="581" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-can-we-extend-power-platform-solutions">How can we extend Power Platform solutions?<a class="hash-link" href="#how-can-we-extend-power-platform-solutions" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>You might wondering how you can leverage your code first skills with the Power Platform. Let's take a look at some ways that we can extend our Power Platform solutions with code (many of these concepts will be covered in more detail in later blog posts).</p><ul><li><strong>UI Components</strong> - Leverage the <a href="https://aka.ms/LowCodePCF" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Power Apps Component Framework</a> to extend the UI of our applications with custom code.</li><li><strong>Custom Connectors</strong> - Create <a href="https://aka.ms/LowCodeCustomConnectors" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">custom connectors</a>, which are essentially a wrapper around an API to communicate to our external data sources and services.</li><li><strong>Custom Visuals in Power BI</strong> - Use the open-source SDK to create <a href="https://aka.ms/LowCodeCustomVisuals" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">custom visuals</a> for your reports and dashboards</li><li><strong>Custom Business Logic</strong> - Extend the <a href="https://aka.ms/LowCodeDataverseAPI" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Dataverse API</a> with your own custom API that implements your business logic</li><li><strong>Add CI/CD</strong> - Setup continuous integration and continuous deployment (<a href="https://aka.ms/LowCodeALM" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">CI/CD</a>) with your Power Platform solutions</li></ul><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Power Platform Pro Dev extensions" src="/Low-Code/assets/images/02_Extend-c65dc3a6bde0fa96c118ff6caffce29b.png" width="1266" height="537" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="whats-next">What's next?<a class="hash-link" href="#whats-next" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>In the next series of posts you'll learn more about some of these core concepts and extension points. </p><p>If all of this sounds intriguing and you want to get started on your low code development journey, here are some actions you can take:</p><ul><li>1️⃣ <a href="https://aka.ms/lowcode-february/devplan" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Sign up</strong></a> for the free Power Apps Developer Plan.</li><li>2️⃣ <a href="https://aka.ms/lowcode-february/challenge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Enroll</strong></a> in the Cloud Skills Challenge to learn more about low code and fusion team fundamentals and start climbing that leaderboard!</li><li>3️⃣ <a href="http://aka.ms/lowcode-february" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Save</strong></a> the page to start your learning on Feb 1, and <a href="https://microsoft.github.io/Low-Code/blog/rss.xml" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Subscribe</strong></a> to the blog in your favorite feed reader for updates.</li></ul><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Empty Banner Placeholder" src="/Low-Code/assets/images/banner-d53c0bd413d511cd5ea292a325526162.png" width="1500" height="630" class="img_ev3q"></p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="resources">Resources<a class="hash-link" href="#resources" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><ul><li><a href="https://aka.ms/LowCodePowerPlatformIntro" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Introduction to the Power Platform</a></li><li><a href="https://aka.ms/FusionDevEbook" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fusion Development with Power Platform EBook</a></li><li><a href="https://aka.ms/learn-fusiondev" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Fusion Development with Power Platform Learning Path</a></li></ul>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>low-code-february</category>
            <category>30-days-of-lowcode</category>
            <category>learn-live</category>
            <category>zero-to-hero</category>
            <category>ask-the-expert</category>
            <category>fusion-teams</category>
            <category>power-platform</category>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[It's a Low Code February!]]></title>
            <link>https://microsoft.github.io/Low-Code/blog/2023-kickoff</link>
            <guid>2023-kickoff</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Welcome to Low Code February!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="welcome-to-low-code-february">Welcome to Low Code February!<a class="hash-link" href="#welcome-to-low-code-february" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>February is traditionally a month where we celebrate family, friends and loved ones - from Valentine's Day to Lunar New Year! We hope you also make this the month you fall in love with a new technology space - <em>low-code app development</em> - and join us for a month of learning, making, and sharing!</p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Post Banner" src="/Low-Code/assets/images/banner-70b2761604f86067387157d843c4eb4e.png" width="1600" height="672" class="img_ev3q"></p><p>We are excited to announce the <strong>launch of #LowCodeFebruary</strong>, a month-long developer journey that will take you from app development tips, to fusion teams insights, and hands-on tutorials to skill you up on Power Platform, Microsoft Azure, and popular developer tools to enhance your productivity.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="what-will-we-cover">What will we cover?<a class="hash-link" href="#what-will-we-cover" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Let's talk about what you will learn in our developer journey this month. We have multiple initiatives in mind that can help you <em>learn</em>, <em>skill up</em>, <em>engage with experts</em>, <em>contribute to community</em> and <em>watch videos</em> at your own pace. </p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="LCF Banner" src="/Low-Code/assets/images/lcf-banner-afd117c7604fa9f2ace6a32a14d7cf15.png" width="1600" height="672" class="img_ev3q"></p><ol><li>The <a href="/Low-Code/blog"><strong>#30DaysOfLowCode</strong></a> blog series helps you <em>learn</em> by reading posts from experts, taking you on a 4-week journey from fundamentals, to application lifecycle managment - and cover developer tools and best practices along the way!</li><li>The <a href="/Low-Code/lowcode-february/ZeroToHero/"><strong>#ZeroToHero</strong></a> series captures blog posts directly from our product teams, sharing the latest features and tips for low code development.</li><li>The <a href="/Low-Code/docs/intro/"><strong>Dev Workshops</strong></a> page will learning tutorials and resources for all levels, from beginner to advanced.Learn how to build scalable apps, manage app lifecycle management with the Azure services and use popular Developer tools for enhanced productivity.  </li><li>The <a href="https://aka.ms/lowcode-february/challenge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Cloud Skills Challenge</strong></a> is a set of curated free, self-guided learning modules <em>focused on fusion teams and low-code development</em>. Complete them in #30Days and make the leaderboard!</li><li>The <a href="/Low-Code/lowcode-february/Video-Live/"><strong>Video + Livestream</strong></a> page showcases live events (e.g., AskTheExpert, LearnLive) and on-demand video shows (e.g., LowCode Revolution) and replays, to help you learn at your own pace. </li><li>The <a href="https://pnp.github.io/powerplatform-samples/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Community Buzz</strong></a> section connects you to peer community members. Share your samples and learn from 90+ real-world Power Platform examples shared by the community. And share your contributions with us via GitHub issues or with a <a href="https://dev.to/t/powerfuldevs" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">post on dev.to usingthe #powerfuldevs tag</a>.</li></ol><h2 class="anchor anchorWithStickyNavbar_LWe7" id="how-can-you-participate">How can you participate?<a class="hash-link" href="#how-can-you-participate" title="Direct link to heading">​</a></h2><p>Want to get started on your low code development journey with us? Here are some actions you can take today:</p><ul><li>1️⃣ <a href="https://aka.ms/lowcode-february/devplan" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Sign up</strong></a> for the free Power Apps Developer Plan.</li><li>2️⃣ <a href="https://aka.ms/lowcode-february/challenge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Enroll</strong></a> in the Cloud Skills Challenge and start climbing that leaderboard!</li><li>3️⃣ <a href="http://aka.ms/lowcode-february" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Save</strong></a> the page to start your learning on Feb 1, and <a href="https://microsoft.github.io/Low-Code/blog/rss.xml" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><strong>Subscribe</strong></a> to the blog in your favorite feed reader for updates. </li></ul><p>Ready to get started being a low-code developer, or a pro-dev supporting fusion teams and low code app development?</p><p>🏁 <strong>#Lets Go!</strong></p><p><img loading="lazy" alt="Technologies used for fusion development" src="/Low-Code/assets/images/01 - Kickoff-b6ff5da871188894bc9935af9614742c.png" width="1600" height="900" class="img_ev3q"></p>]]></content:encoded>
            <category>low-code-february</category>
            <category>30-days-of-lowcode</category>
            <category>learn-live</category>
            <category>zero-to-hero</category>
            <category>ask-the-expert</category>
            <category>fusion-teams</category>
            <category>power-platform</category>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>